All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף
daf is צדי Tzadi and we're wrapping up the ninth פרק. perek.
We start at the bottom
of פ"ט עמוד ב' Pey-Tes Amud Bais at the
משנה. Mishnah. So we just went through a whole discussion about collecting
the כתובה Ketubah and what type of evidence is needed if the
husband brings just the כתובה, Ketubah, the husband, the wife brings just
the כתובה Ketubah or just the גט. Get. Now let's take a
look at this next משנה Mishnah which touches on some issues we've
seen before.
שני גיטין ושתי כתובות, Shnei Gittin u-Shtei Ketubot, a woman produces two
גיטין Gittin and two כתובות. Ketubot. Okay, and they are, yes, same
person. And they're staggered, right? So the כתובה, Ketubah, I don't know,
was from 1980 and the גט Get was from 1990. And then
the next כתובה Ketubah was from 2000 and the גט Get was
from 2010. So it sounds like there was a marriage, divorce, marriage,
divorce. Okay. So, and the timing is right, the staggering is right.
גובה שתי כתובות, Gova shtei ketubot, she can collect two כתובות Ketubot
because although some people might remember we talked before that if there's
a divorce and a remarriage, it's a continuation of the same כתובה,
Ketubah, that's the default. But למעשה le-ma'aseh if the husband wants and
goes ahead and writes a second כתובה, Ketubah, then he's obligated in
a second
כתובה. Ketubah. שתי כתובות וגט אחד. Shtei Ketubot ve-Get Echad. Now let's
say the כתובה Ketubah was from 1980, 1990, and one from 1980,
1990, and then a גט Get in the year 2000. So in
those cases, oh, כתובה ושני גיטין, Ketubah u-Shnei Gittin, or there was
one כתובה Ketubah and two גיטין, Gittin, okay. כתובה Ketubah 1980, גט
Get in 1990 and 2000, and a גט Get in 2000. או
כתובה וגט ומיתה. O Ketubah ve-Get u-Misah. Now that's an obvious case,
right? גט Get in 1980, כתובה Ketubah 1980, גט Get 1990, the
guy died in 2000. אינו גובה אלא כתובה אחת. Eino gova ela
Ketubah achas. She only collects once. So the last case is of
course obvious, right? First she got divorced and then her husband died,
she doesn't collect again as a widow. Okay, the case of one
כתובה Ketubah and two גיטין, Gittin, which is evidence that he remarried
her, here's the principle that without the active, the proactive writing of
a second כתובה, Ketubah, a remarriage, which is interesting, right, a remarriage
does not, would not entitle her automatically to a second כתובה. Ketubah.
Remarriage to the same guy, the first כתובה Ketubah continues to be
the, you know, it's sort of like all on the basis of
that original כתובה Ketubah unless he chose to rewrite a second כתובה.
Ketubah. And the case of two כתובות Ketubot and one גט Get
is interesting. What is that supposed to mean?
So we'll take a look here more.
Well, you might think that they both should be active and both
she could use both, like he wanted to give her even an
additional right, an extra right. And actually if you might remember we
had a case before where the, where it was a case about
the עד אחד ed echad or whatever and the גמרא Gemara spoke
about a scenario where she had two כתובות Ketubot and she could
use both of them. So that's going to be a question. Why
there she could only use one, and then also which one? Okay,
so in those cases, אינו גובה אלא כתובה אחת, eino gova ela
Ketubah achas, שמא גירשה הימנו והחזירה, shema geresha ito ve-hichzirah, והחזירן, ve-hichziran,
and this is the case that the משנה Mishnah felt needed explaining.
The case of one כתובה Ketubah and two גיטין. Gittin. He divorces
his wife and remarries her על מנת כתובה הראשונה מחזירה. al m'nas
Ketubah ha-rishonah machazirah. So it's all on the basis of the original
כתובה Ketubah with the, with the assumption again, he could obviously explicitly
give her a second כתובה, Ketubah, but without doing that there's an
assumption that the first כתובה Ketubah is going to be what is
going to be binding for the second marriage as well.
Yes, so clarification, she's married, she gets divorced. She marries someone else,
gets divorced. She can't go back to the first.
Of course, well, if she never collected her כתובה Ketubah from her
first husband, she could. Sure.
That's what I want to clarify.
Yeah. Just because her second husband owes her a כתובה, Ketubah, she
can still, her first
husband literally getting married, literally she gets remarried. You're talking about the
money.
What?
You're just talking about the money, right? She can't remarry the first
guy if she had married somebody else in between.
Right, that's the איסור issur in the תורה Torah about remarriage after
marriage, oh right, right, right. But I didn't understand what you meant
go back.
Yeah, she could actually collect
that, yes, yes, yes, right, but
she's not remarry her first husband after she has a, after another
man in between. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעיא
להו בהאי גוונא, iba'aya leh be-hai gavna, איבעיא להו בהאי גוונא. iba'aya
leh be-hai gavna. So it sounds like if there are two כתובות,
Ketubot, so we're going to assume that they're not both binding, but
it does sound like she can choose which one to use, right?
Now there's a benefit, it might depend which one she wants to
use. The earlier one has earlier liens. So there's the benefit of
using that. The later one might be a higher dollar amount or
something. So it sounds like it's her choice which one to use
because it says she only has one, but it doesn't say which
one. So the גמרא Gemara says: לימא דהוי תיובתא דרב נחמן אמר
שמואל? leima de-havei tiyuvta de-Rav Nachman amar Shmuel? Let's say this contradicts
Rav Nachman amar Shmuel? דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל: de-amar Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel: שני שטרות היוצאים זה אחר זה,
shnei shtaros ha-yotzin zeh
achar zeh, ביטל שני את הראשון. bitel sheni es ha-rishon. If there
are two שטרות shtaros that come sequentially and somehow it's obvious, it's
not clear exactly how it's obvious, but somehow it's obvious that they
refer to the same transaction. Okay, but one comes later than the
other. The easier way to explain it would be, easiest way to
explain it is it's the same plot of land. Okay, so So
then you know clearly that they're not two separate, but if it's
one is you borrowed a hundred dollars from me and in January
and then the next one is in February you borrowed a hundred
dollars from me, maybe you borrowed a hundred dollars from me twice.
Okay, so but the easier case is that you bought this plot
of land from me in January and then another שטר shtar says
you bought this plot of land from me from February. So he
says the second one overrides the first. You don't have a choice
which one to use. Again, what's the benefit of using the earlier
one? The earlier one has earlier liens. Even if I'm selling you
a plot of land, there's a benefit of having earlier liens because
if the assumption is that I also accept the responsibility, so I
sold you this plot of land and then some creditor comes and
takes that land away from you because I owe that guy money.
You come back to me for your money back. So now you
have liens on my property for the sale, so you want earlier
liens as well. So anyway, the earlier bill of sale is generally
more better. Or you just want to prove you owned the property,
oil was found on the property, right? So you want to prove
you owned it from an earlier time. So nevertheless what he says
is is that if you have these two sequential
documents, so בטלה שנייה את הראשונה, batla shniya es harishona, the second
one overrides the first. Okay, so and here it sounds like you
can choose which one to use. Okay, now רש"י Rashi says the
logic that the second one overrides the first is, nobody forced you
to accept the second document. If you accepted the second document, okay,
and רש"י Rashi writes the second document, the later one, usually hurts
your position. Again, lesser liens, you owned it from less time, owned
it for less time. You are implicitly saying I am waiving the
rights or the liens that I had earlier and I'm willing to
accept the second document which makes it like I only owned the
land or I only had those liens at a later time. Okay,
so the very fact that you accepted the second document, right, means
that you gave up the rights you had from the first one.
So if I buy, I buy some land from you? Yes. And
creditor comes and takes it because there was a lien because you
owed them money? Right. I can then go to you and get
my money back? Because it was my, it was my obligation to
do title search and to make sure...
Yeah, so that's the right. So there's the question about under what
circumstances do you assume that when I sell something to you I
sell it with אחריות achrayus
or
not or not. Okay, so yeah, but there are cases...
And it may be okay in the bill?
I mean, I understand, but the question is who's...
anyway, so yes, you know, that's a legitimate
question, but there are cases either I explicitly accept that responsibility on
myself or there's a we're doing it with a presumption that I
accept the responsibility on myself, but we could also I could always
exempt myself from that responsibility.
The actual legal shot of the term אחריות achrayus when it you're
talking about שעבוד? shibud? Right. Who assumes responsibility for the lien in
the case of a creditor coming?
Exactly. Yeah. Okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So בטלה שנייה את הראשונה. batla shniya es harishona. So here it
sounds like she can choose which one to use. Why don't we
say the very fact that she accepted a second כתובה kesubah means
that she gave up the rights to her first כתובה? kesubah? So
גמרא Gemara says, but איתמר עלה אמר רב פפא, itmar ala amar
Rav Papa, one minute, it was said to qualify this, רב פפא
Rav Papa said, ומודו אביי ורבא דאי הוסיף בה דקלא לתוספת כתבה,
umodu Abaye v'Rava d'ei hosif bah dikla l'tosefes kesavah,
that if I added on it a palm tree, then I wrote
it for the additional thing. So I gave you this well, yes,
meaning I went ahead and wrote you a second document to this
plot of land and on the second document I I gave you
one extra palm tree, one extra square inch than the first document
had. So therefore you would say, okay, so all the more reason
why you want the second document. No, because then the assumption is
that I am somehow empowering you to choose which document you prefer.
If clearly the second one is worse than the first and you
accepted the second, that meant that you were willing to give up
your rights to the first. But if there's an element in which
the second one is better than the first, it's got an extra
square inch of property, it's got an extra palm tree, then maybe
what you're doing is I'm giving it to you and giving you
the option to choose which one is more in your interest. The
one with later ownership, later liens, but extra amount, or the one
with earlier ownership, earlier liens, but less amount. Okay, so since the
second one is not clearly worse than the first, by accepting the
second you're not waiving the first, you're giving yourself the freedom to
choose. All right. Yes. So that's
why and that's why our משנה Mishna assumes that she can choose
which one to use. Okay, so אמר רב פפא ומודו אביי ורבא
דאי הוסיף בה דקלא לתוספת כתבה. amar Rav Papa umodu Abaye v'Rava
d'ei hosif bah dikla l'tosefes kesavah. הכא נמי בדאוסיף לה. hacha nami
bid'osif lah. So here too, the second כתובה kesubah would have, let's
say, an it would be even if it had just one dollar
more of debt to it, then the fact that she accepts it
means that she's going to choose whether she'd like the one
with a higher dollar amount and later liens or with a lesser
dollar amount and earlier liens. Again, she had the two כתובות kesubos
and noted
that there was some detail that was different between the two. Right.
Although our משנה Mishna didn't say there were two כתובות. kesubos. Didn't
say that one was only a dollar more. Okay, that's the גמרא's
Gemara way to do it. Now, it is possible that you actually
have a double debt, which is if you explicitly wrote in the
second כתובה, kesubah, in addition to the first debt, I'm also obligating
myself into this second debt. Then it would obviously be A and
B, A and B. But this way it's A or B. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, הוציאה
גט וכתובה ומיתה, hotziah get u'kesubah u'misah, so she took out her
גט get together with... with a כתובה kesuvah and death. That’s for
the facts. עם גט, im get, right. Exactly. Let’s take a look.
That’s what it says. Okay. And he basically wants to say, you
know, first he divorced me, and then he remarried me, and then
he died, so I get two כתובות. kesuvos. Okay, so let’s see
what’s that. אם גט קודם לכתובה, im get kodem l'kesuvah, so גובה
שתי כתובות. gova shtei kesuvos. If the גט get was dated before
the כתובה, kesuvah, so then
she does get two. He divorced her, she gets a כתובה kesuvah
from the first marriage, the later dated כתובה kesuvah is indication that
he remarried her with a new כתובה. kesuvah. He didn’t have to
write a new כתובה kesuvah but he chose to, so that creates
a new obligation and then he dies and then she collects as
an אלמנה. almanah. כתובה קודמת לגט, kesuvah kodemes l'get, if the כתובה
kesuvah preceded the גט, get, אינה גובה אלא כתובה אחת, eina gova
ela kesuvah achas, then she only gets one because even though clearly
he divorced her and then let’s say even we have evidence that
he remarried her, it doesn’t matter. שהמגרש את אשתו והחזירה, she-hamigaresh es
ishto ve-hechezirah, that if he divorced his wife and remarried
her, על מנת כתובה הראשונה החזירה, al menas kesuvah ha-rishonah hechezirah, then
she does not get a second כתובה kesuvah because of the second
marriage unless that was explicitly done. Okay, so that’s just a nice
clarification of the whatever, repeat of the משנה. mishnah. Next משנה, mishnah,
final משנה mishnah of the פרק. perek. קטן שהשיאו אביו. katan she-hisio
aviv. If a minor boy was married off by his father. We’ve
always been talking about a minor girl being married off by her
father, but you see how much different their society was. Sometimes actually
a father would choose to marry off his son and again not
just to arrange a marriage, but actually they’ll start like living together.
השיאו נשואין, hisio nisuin, right, which is very strange because you might
remember and it’s always worth repeating, because that’s right, so it’s not
biblically binding and it’s always worth repeating that even though we talk
about קידושי קטנה, kiddushei ketanah, the גמרא gemara made it very clear
that the נשואין, nisuin, right, would not happen until she was, they’re
actually living together would not happen until she was like a נערה.
na'arah. Okay, so she at least was twelve and a half. Okay,
but
to us still that's a little still a little shocking but, you
know, anyway, I mean, it does happen that people are having sex
at that age. But anyway at least it wasn’t younger than that.
Nevertheless, here you have a case of נשואי nisuei of not, of
נשואים, nisuim, actually living together and the boy is a קטן.
katan. Maybe he’s older so she can make him lunch.
Maybe right exactly. So in this case, כתובתה קיימת kesubasah kayamas and
a כתובה kesuvah was written for the girl or woman. Okay, so
that remains, now that wasn’t, he wasn’t able to legally obligate himself
in a כתובה kesuvah because he was a קטן. katan. Nevertheless, now
that he becomes an adult, that כתובה kesuvah is binding. שהמנת כן
קיימה, she-al menas kein kiymah, because with that understanding he kept her
as a wife when he became an adult, based on the original,
based on whatever the right, the original כתובה kesuvah was. גר שנתגיירה
אשתו עמו. ger she-nisgayerah ishto imo. Now let’s say a husband and
wife convert, and they have a כתובה kesuvah from their lives as
non-Jews. Because apparently there was such a thing as marriage documents that
non-Jews did as well, which apparently this was not a uniquely Jewish
institution. I know, it doesn't say פסק לה כתובה כדת משה וישראל,
pasak lah kesuvah kedas Moshe v'Yisrael, but it lists how much the
dowry was, it lists how much he would pay her in the
advent of a divorce or death. So here we have a very
fascinating little historical event buried in this משנה mishnah that non-Jews did
something that pretty much paralleled the כתובה kesuvah institution. It
might not have had the question about מעשה ידיהם ma'aseh yadeihem and
those types of things, but presumably the lump sum payment amount or
whatever was a reality. I again don’t know what the
would they constantly trust the non-Jewish עדים?
edim? I don't know, let’s take a look. Okay. So כתובתה קיימת,
kesubasah kayamas, it’s still binding. שהמנת כן קיימה she-al menas kein kiymah
that now that they’re Jews and they stayed married it was with
that understanding. So it sounds like the point is that even if
there was like an amount written more than the hundred and the
two hundred, whatever that amount was is considered to still be the
amount you’re committing yourselves to now that you’re in a meaningful situation
to be obligated. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
gemara says.
Wait a second, I’m sorry, could you just explain the facts of
this גר שנתגיירה
אשתו?
ger
she-nisgayerah ishto? Yeah, yeah. He was a גר. ger.
Christine and Christopher
were
married and they wrote and basically in their non-Jewish world they also
wrote a document that said if I die or divorce you you’ll
be entitled to a certain amount of a lump sum payment and
here’s the amount you brought in in your dowry and whatever and
all that was written in some document in Greek or whatever it
was. Okay, and then they both decided to convert. Okay, and now
they're both Jewish and they didn’t rewrite a כתובה kesuvah and they’re
staying married together and then he dies. What’s she entitled to collect?
So it says she’s entitled to collect based whatever in the, whatever’s
in that marriage document, that Greek marriage document from before they converted
because now that they converted and stayed married together it’s done with
the, in the context and the assumption of maintaining those earlier obligations.
But it sounds like Christopher’s already Jewish.
No, נתגיירה אשתו עמו nisgayerah ishto imo means they both converted. Yeah,
exactly, exactly, yeah, that’s the עמו, imo, like at the same time.
Okay, but my question was, if ever contested, like so they’re gonna
trust non-Jewish עדים edim to say like this is what was in
there, you know.
Yeah, I mean there are questions in the whole מסכת גיטין Masechet
Gittin about certain documents that are יוצאים בערכאות של גויים yotzim be'arka'ot
shel goyim that you actually might, you know, might trust, you know,
or whatever could be valid. Okay, so it says like this: אמר
רב הונא Amar Rav Huna לא שנו אלא מנה ומאתיים. lo shanu
ela maneh umatayim. So he gives a read of the Mishnah which
clearly does not sound like פשט. pshat. It says it was only
talking about the base amount. Okay, now of course the base amount,
who needed there to be an earlier כתובה? ketubah? Any marriage, right,
is obligated in the base amount. Okay, אלמנה מאתיים. Almanah matayim. אבל
תוספת אין לה, Aval tosefet ein lah,
whatever the additional amount was from that earlier period, that does not
become part of the obligation. רב יהודה אמר אפילו תוספת יש לה.
Rav Yehuda amar afilu tosefet yesh lah. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
even the additional amount, which seems like the point of the Mishnah.
Interestingly, we're going to come out siding with רב הונא. Rav Huna.
מתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you: חידשו, Chidshu, if there's a תוספתא Tosefta
that says if they innovated something, meaning after now they converted or
after now the minor became an adult, they added an additional amount
to the
כתובה, ketubah, נוטלת מה שחידשו, noteles mah she'chidshu, she's entitled to the
additional amount. So the גמרא Gemara assumes what that means is only
the additional amount, only the amount that they added afterwards. חידשו אין,
Chidshu in, if they added something now that they're in this, you
know, Jewish adult state, then
that's what you can get beyond the base amount. But לא חידשו
לא, lo chidshu lo, without that, it sounds like you can't get
anything beyond the base amount.
This
is
Christopher or Christopher, yeah, or Johnny who now is an adult. So
the גמרא Gemara says no: לא, אימא אף מה שחידשו. Lo, eima
af mah she'chidshu. No,
it means if they added now that he's an adult or now
that they've converted, then she gets also what was added now, but
she still gets the full amount from before. So the fact that
she gets what was added now doesn't prove that she doesn't get
the full amount from before. So the גמרא Gemara says no: והא
לא תני הכי, Ve'ha lo tani hachi, but that's not what the
full text says. Here's what the text says: חידשו, Chidshu, if they
added an additional amount now that, you know, they're Jewish and adult,
נוטלת מה שחידשו, noteles mah she'chidshu, she gets that additional amount; לא
חידשו, lo chidshu, and if they didn't add an additional amount, בתולה
גובה מאתיים ואלמנה מנה. besulah govah matayim ve'almanah maneh.
So then you only get the base amount, even though presumably the
כתובה ketubah from before was larger. תיובתא דרב יהודה תיובתא. Tyufta de'Rav
Yehuda tyufta. So that is a תיובתא דרב יהודה. tyufta de'Rav Yehuda.
That is a complete contradiction to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. The ברייתא
braita is explicit that you don't get anything beyond the base amount.
So the גמרא Gemara says: רב יהודה מתניתין אטעיתיה. Rav Yehuda matnitin
ateiteih. And you know, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was misled by the
language of the Mishnah, right? Because the Mishnah says: הוא סבר כתובתה
קיימת אכולה מילתא. hu savar ketubatah kayamet akula milta.
It says, right, it says כתובתה קיימת, ketubatah kayamet, she still gets
the כתובה. ketubah. It sounds like אכולה מילתא, akula milta, the
whole thing, but לא, אכולה מילתא lo, akula milta just means the
base כתובה. ketubah. So תוספות Tosafot asks, you know, come on, רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda sounds like it's פשט. pshat. Why do you need
a Mishnah to tell me you get the כתובה ketubah based on
the earlier thing if any married couple gets the 200 or the
100? So תוספות Tosafot says, look at תוספות: Tosafot: דאם תאמר de'im
tomar תוספות, Tosafot, אי הכי מאי קמשמע לן מתניתין? ee hachi mai
kamashma lan matnitin? What's it teaching in the Mishnah? Oh,
it was in this context they stayed married, אפילו לא כתב לה
מעולם, afilu lo katav lah me'olam, even if they never had a
prior כתובה, ketubah, יש לה כתובה, yesh lah ketubah, because, you know,
the Rabbis instituted it. Okay. And then תוספות Tosafot says, I'll skip
like four lines from the end, beginning of the line, and תוספות
Tosafot has a brilliant read of the Mishnah: ויש לומר Veyesh lomar
דאשמעינן היכא דניסא בתולה de'ashmianu heicha denisa besulah אף על גב דחשי
גדלה ונתגיירה כשהיא בעולה af al gav de'chasha gadla venitgayera kshehi beulah
אפילו הכי יש לה כתובה מאתיים. afilu hachi yesh lah ketubah matayim.
The חידוש chiddush is, is that when they got married, Chris and
Christopher and Christine, she was a בתולה. besulah. And now they converted,
and she's no longer בתולה. besulah. So forget any written כתובה. ketubah.
How much does she get, 100 or 200? So the answer is,
ah, she gets 200 because they were first married it was as
a בתולה. besulah. And therefore their staying married and therefore it's understood
that it follows that original context that defines their original relationship, even
though that original relationship, the כתובה ketubah obligation was not yet binding.
Okay, or similar in this case of the קטן, katan, right? The
girl or the woman is now a בעולה beulah and that was
not yet a binding obligation. Nevertheless, as they continue married and it's
a continuation of that earlier context, it's defined as a marriage to
a בתולה besulah when they were non-Jews.
Immaculate conception. There you go. Alright. Anyway, so that at least explains
what the point of the Mishnah is, although again, it seems that
the simple פשט pshat is רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. Nevertheless, we are
saying no, it's only the base amount, but at least the base
amount defined by her state when they were originally married. הדרן עלך
כותב לאשתו, Hadran alach kotev le'ishto, and that is the end of
that פרק. perek. Okay, so that ends the question about, you know,
what type of evidence she has to bring, when she can be
exempted from certain types of שבועות shavuot to prove that, you know,
she hasn't collected, and so on. Now we move on, is there
two documents, only one document, you know, two כתובות, ketubas, two גיטין,
gittin, etc. Now we move on to... Competing claims against the estate,
which is a different topic, which is going to be the focus
of this פרק *perek*. Yeah?
Doesn't this little tiny סיפא *seifa* of this little tiny משנה Mishnah
*mishnah* fly in the face of that entire theme of non-Jews of
viciscentious, their sexual mores are so loose, they don't
know—you mean the fact that it's still assumed to be a בתולה
*besulah*? Okay, that's a good point. Right. According to תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*,
we assume the context of a בתולה *besulah*. Yeah.
That's a good point.
Tiny little
thing
with a gigantic subtext about their lack of morals.
You're right, it's an excellent, excellent point. Excellent. Okay, thank you. No,
thank you. Very nice. Exactly. Okay. משנה. Mishnah מי שהיה נשוי שתי
נשים *Mishnah. Mi shehaya nasui shtei nashim*—somebody who was married to two
wives—ומת *umes*—and he died. הראשונה קודמת לשניה *Harishonah kodemes lashniyah*—the first one
has earlier liens on the estate and now coming to collect the
כתובה kesubah, *kesubah*, okay, and maybe there's a limited estate. So it's
like two creditors. So the one with the earlier liens has the
right to collect first. And if there's not enough left over afterwards,
tough luck on the second person.
Okay. ויורשי הראשונה קודמים ליורשי שניה *Veyorshei harishonah kodmim leyorshei shniyah*. Now
let's say after the guy died, or after he divorced let's say
both of his wives, but here it says he died. After he
died, then both of the wives died after he did. Okay. So
then the heirs are coming to collect. They're still heirs of their
mothers who were creditors and the heirs of the earlier creditor of
the earlier wife has rights for before the heirs of the later
wife. קודמים ליורשי שניה *Kodmim leyorshei shniyah*. Now, נשא את הראשונה ומתה
נשא שניה ומת הוא *Nasa es harishonah umesah nasa shniyah umes hu*.
So he married the first one and she died. What happens when
she died? He inherited her. So her heirs are going to be
out. Except, let's remember the principle of כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvos Benin
Dichrin, *kesubas benin dichrin*. Okay. כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvos Benin Dichrin. *Kesubas
benin dichrin* is exactly for a case like this, that he has
two wives. So basically here's what he did. He married the first
wife and okay, so let's say again the base is 200. Everybody
gets 200. But she brought in a huge dowry and he had
to write her a huge תוספת tosefet *tosefes* because she came from
a very wealthy family. So her dowry was $10,000, her
תוספת tosefes. *tosefes* was another $10,000. So basically the amount of the
כתובה kesuva *kesubah* was $20,000 and 200. Okay. Now if he would
have divorced her or died first, that's how much she would have
taken out of the estate. He didn't. She died first. Okay. But
here's the thing: her heirs, if she has heirs with him, and
he has other heirs from another wife, her heirs—the heirs of her
children—are going to first get $20,000 out of the estate as part
of their inheritance. Okay, because that's the amount the mother brought in.
So although he inherited her, when it's finally his time to pass
and die, his children with her are going to get that chunk
of money. That's כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvos Benin Dichrin. *kesubas benin dichrin*.
Okay, so she died, then he married a second woman, maybe had
kids with her, whatever, then—and then what happened?—he died. Okay. So now
the heirs of wife number one—we'll call them רחל Rachel, *Rachel* and
לאה Leah, *Leah*—רחל's Rochel *Rachel's* heirs are coming to get their mother's
portion as an inheritance, כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvos Benin Dichrin, *kesubas benin
dichrin*. The heirs of לאה *Leah* are coming to get—because לאה's *Leah's*
an אלמנה *almanah*, because he died before לאה *Leah*, right, he died
before לאה *Leah*—are coming to get their mother's כתובה kesuva, *kesubah*, which
might be, I don't know, 10,000 and 200.
Who knows what that amount was? They're coming to get that as
the collection of the כתובה kesuva, *kesubah*, essentially as creditors. That's money
owed to them, right? They're not as heirs. That's money that was
owed to the mother. The mother could have still been alive. The
mother could come to be collecting that, but she died first—first he
died,
and then let's say לאה *Leah* died or whatever. The fact that
we're talking about לאה's *Leah's* heirs makes it a little bit confusing,
but we could be talking about לאה *Leah*. Okay. So לאה *Leah*
is now coming to get her portion not as an heir but
as a creditor. All right?
So inheritance versus debt.
Right. So נשא את הראשונה ומתה נשא שניה ומת הוא *Nasa es
harishonah umesah nasa shniyah umes hu*. שניה ויורשיה *Shniyah veyorsheha*—לאה *Leah* and/or
her heirs—קודמים ליורשי ראשונה *kodmim leyorshei rishonah*. Get their piece out before
רחל's Rochel *Rachel's* kids because a creditor precedes the heirs, right? Somebody
dies and there's a creditor that has a $10,000 lien on the
estate, right, debt on the estate, he's entitled to take that state—that's
the whole point. He takes that property from away from the heirs,
right? He's got a debt against the estate. So לאה *Leah* and
her kids have a debt against the estate that they take out
before we discuss any of it passing to רחל's *Rachel's* kids. Okay.
So you could construct the כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvos Benin Dichrin *kesubas
benin dichrin* as a debt also, right? You could have.
Yes, but we're assuming that it's correct. And that was a question
about whether ירתון תנן *yartan tnan* or ינחלון תנן *yanchalon tnan*. We're
assuming that it's seen as a debt—okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I mean, we're assuming it's seen as an
inheritance. מדקתני
*Mid'katani*—so first we're going to start on the first part. מדקתני *Mid'katani*
that it's just a simple case that he dies and the question
is wife one, wife two, who's the earlier creditor? coming to collect
the money owed to them as a debt. מדקתני הראשונה קודמת לשניה,
the first one gets has rights before the second one, ולא קתני
הראשונה יש לה והשניה אין לה, velo katani harishona yesh lah vehashniya
ein lah,
the first one gets the property and not the second one, so
it sounds like it is just a question of
who comes first, but not fundamentally that the second one is excluded.
מכלל דאי קדמה שניה ותפסה לא מפקינן מינה. mikhlal de'ei kadma shniya
vetafsa lo mafkinan minah.
It sounds like there is an order, but if the second one
jumped in front of the line and she grabbed the property first,
you do not take it away from her. Now that is a
funny deal, because you could say that even if there is enough
property in the estate, maybe the person with the first liens gets
the right to choose which property, even saying comes first there might
be scenarios of coming first where it is important to say comes
first even if the second one isn't fully excluded, but it is
a strange anyway it is a strange דיוק diyuk that because it
uses that language that means that the second one, if they jumped
ahead, are entitled to it. Number one. Number two is there is
a huge תוספות Tosafot. here who says, I don't understand it, תוספות.
Tosafot Let's assume the second one can get and the first one
can't use their liens. Let's assume that the second one actually purchased
the property, paid good money for the property, right? Somebody came, I
have liens on an estate, and Charlie there comes ahead and he
buys that property from the person who borrowed money from me, and
he paid good money. What am I entitled to do now if
the guy isn't paying up his debt? I can take that property
away from Charlie, right? Even though Charlie paid good money. Okay, so
now let's have another scenario. Charlie didn't pay money, Charlie lent money
to the guy, the guy didn't pay him up, and then Charlie
went ahead and he took the property, okay, but he came after
me. Why should I not be able to go take that property
away from Charlie? I can take the property away from Charlie if
he bought it, so here Charlie has a later lien and he's
taking the property, right?
I have an earlier lien, I should be able to take the
property away from Charlie. So תוספות Tosafot I can't understand what this
גמרא Gemara. the הוה אמינא hava amina here is. Let's read the
next line of the גמרא. Gemara מכלל דאי קדמה שניה ותפסה לא
מפקינן מינה. mikhlal de'ei kadma shniya vetafsa lo mafkinan minah. שמע מינה
בעל חוב מאוחר, shema mina ba'al hov me'uhar, a later creditor, שקדם
וגבה מה שגבה גבה,
shekadam
vegava
mah shegava gava, that jumped ahead in line and grabbed the property,
מה שגבה גבה, mah shegava gava, he's entitled to it. So this
huge תוספות Tosafot. says what type of, look at the first line
of תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says תימה מה סברא היא
זו. teima mah sevara hi zo. What type of logic is this?
דלא יהא בעל חוב אלא כלוקח. dilo yei ba'al hov ela keloke'ah.
Let him be like he purchased it. דלוקח גופיה קא טריף בעל
חוב ראשון. deloke'ah gufeh ka taraf ba'al hov rishon. I could take
it if the guy bought it after my loan.
Why can't I take it just because he's got a later debt?
So what? Get in line buddy, and if you did take it
I'll take it away from you. So there's a fascinating answer תוספות
Tosafot. has, which is basically one more of social policy. ותירץ רשב"ם,
vetiretz Rashbam, he says the רשב"ם Rashbam says, where
are you reading? eighth line? תוספות. Tosafot
Did I skip a line?
down down down...
גופיה קא טריף בעל חוב ראשון.
gufeh
ka taraf ba'al hov rishon.
ותירץ רשב"ם דבעל חוב מאוחר עדיף מלוקח. vetiretz Rashbam deba'al hov me'uhar
adif miloke'ah.
Actually in this case Charlie would be able to keep it even
though if he had purchased it he would not. שלא תנעול דלת
בפני לווין, shelo tin'ol delet bifnei lovin,
because there's actually a social policy
that is being served, that if I actually I want to give
all creditors an opportunity to seize property. If I have to worry
that I am not going to lend you property because there are
ten other creditors in line behind me, I am not going to
lend you property. And so if we tell me, I am not
going to lend you money, excuse me. So if we tell me
that
actually even though it's true they are in line behind you, if
you jump ahead of them in the line you'll be able to
keep it, then that'll be a reason for me to lend money.
Of course תוספות Tosafot says no, then actually I'll never lend you
money because I'll say why should I lend you money? Somebody's going
to lend me money after me and he's going to go ahead
and jump in front of me and not whatever. תוספות Tosafot
okay, but then at least everybody has an option has the possibility
of jumping in first. And everybody assumes they'll be able to jump
in first. Okay, but why don't we say that therefore that'll stop
people from buying
property? Anyway תוספות Tosafot basically says that this might be necessary although
there's an unfairness to this, this might be necessary because you need
people to make sure that people keep on lending money and therefore
you want this option to be there, okay? Which is pretty interesting.
He says, וכן כתובת אשה משום חינא vechen ktuvat isha mishum hina
וכי תימא אי מה שגבה גבה איכא נעילת דלת מבעל חוב ראשון.
vechi teima ei mah shegava gava ika ne'ilat delet miba'al hov rishon.
So if you let a later guy seize it, the first guy
will never lend money. תוספות says לא היא הא דהוא יכול לקדם
הוא עצמו לא ימנע מלהלוות, lo hi ha dehu yakhol lekadem hu
atzmo lo yimana milahalvot, אבל אם מה שגבה לא גבה איכא נעילת
דלת דמפסיד בעל
חוב
מאוחר
לגמרי.
aval im mah shegava lo gava
ika ne'ilat delet demafsid ba'al hov me'uhar legamri. Okay,
and then he goes on to discuss whether that's really an answer,
but he points out that this is completely bizarre and that maybe
it's a fascinating issue about what types of trade-offs do we make
when we give people certain types of rights and in terms of
but you need money to be lent. And somebody keeps on getting
deeper and deeper in a hole, right, you know, if Charlie there
has limited property and he keeps on getting borrowing and not being
able to repay, people are going to stop lending him money. So,
you know, obviously at a certain point people should stop lending him
money because they're not going to get it back. But there's a
middle stage where you don't want people to be necessarily overly cautious.
Okay? So, yeah, well it's closing the door
מפני לווין mifnei lovin because if Charlie couldn't jump in first and
recoup to pay you back, you wouldn't loan him money in other
words.
No, no, no. I'm sorry, I switched from Charlie being a whatever.
So I'm sorry, I switched to David is the guy borrowing the
money let's say, okay?
So I lend him money. If Charlie... now he has
a... no so he's got... hold on, let me back up. Okay,
so he's got a limited amount of property and he hasn't been
able to pay me back and now he needs more money. So
he goes to Charlie. So Charlie, if Charlie would say... now at
a certain point if he keeps on borrowing, borrowing money and has
very little collateral, then people shouldn't be lending him money. I mean
it's never for him but, you know, it's just throwing their money
away. But there's this middle stage where it's not such a bad
risk to give it to him. But if Charlie knew that he
would never get any... he would never have any liens because I
have all the earlier liens, he would never have any ability then
I'm not lending him more money because I'm not throwing good money
after bad and Charlie's not lending him money. So that's a situation
where we want people to be willing to take a little bit
of a risk, you know, and it's better for
the order of...
so even though, even
though
if Charlie and I go to בית דין Beis Din and we
all act in a nice מענטשליך menschlich way or whatever, I'm going
to have to go first and I have first rights, maybe we'll
allow for the possibility that if Charlie jumps ahead and seizes it
that he'll be able to keep it.
So this explains Jewish behavior at קידוש. Kiddush.
Exactly! Well, that was well said. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, so that's what it sounds like, it's trying to
be מדייק medayek that from the language of קודם kodem which sounds
like you come first but the other person maybe isn't totally cut
out. So the גמרא Gemara. says,
no. לעולם אימא לך Le'olam eima lach מה שגבה לא גבה ma
she-gava lo gava that if the second guy jumped ahead he does
not get to keep it.
ומאי קדמת Umai kodemet and what does it mean the first wife
comes first? לגמרי Legamri fully comes first, the second one is totally
cut out. So even though it says first, it really means she's
the only one. כי דתנן Ki-de-tnan like didn't we have that sometimes
like we saw in the משנה Mishnah לגמרי קתני legamri ktani כי
דתנן ki-de-tnan בן קודם לבת ben kodem le-bat the son comes before
the daughter in inheritance, which really means that if there's a son
and daughter, he's the one that gets it and she doesn't get
it. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some say מדלא קתני mi-de-lo ktani אם
קדמה שניה ותפסה אין מוציאין מידה im kadma shniya ve-tafsa ein motzi'in
mi-yada some say start at the opposite way. Since it doesn't say
explicitly that if the second one jumped ahead and grabbed the property
she gets to keep it, מכלל דאם קדמה שניה ותפסה מפקינן מינה
mikhlal d'im kadma shniya ve-tafsa mafki'inan mineih so therefore even if she
were to jump ahead and grab it we would take it away
from her. שמע מינה בעל חוב מאוחר שקדם וגבה מה שגבה לא
גבה Shma mina ba'al chov me'uchar she-kadam ve-gava ma she-gava lo gava
so from that we can infer that even if a later one
jumps ahead and seizes it, it is not entitled to keep it.
לעולם... right, so we try the opposite direction, and says no, לעולם
אימא לך מה שגבה גבה. I can tell you that if the
later one grabbed it, it's collected, it's seized, she gets to keep
it. איידי דתני Aidi de-tani שניה ויורשי shniya ve-yorshe קודמין ליורשי ראשונה
kodmin le-yorshe rishona but since later in the ברייתא braisa we use
the language... we speak we say, you know, the second ones who
have the debt come before the first ones who have the inheritance,
so תני רישא tani reisha the beginning we also just used the
phrase of נמי nami ראשונה קודמת לשניה rishona kodemes le-shniya the first
one comes first, but comes first doesn't mean the second one is
necessarily fully cut out. It might just mean comes first, but if
the second one grabs it maybe she gets it. So we haven't
answered that question, we have the amazing possibility that somebody with later
liens, although they have a weaker, you know, although they really need
to get in the back of the line might be able in
some circumstances to go ahead and grab it and seize it. Right?
I mean I think sometimes when a company goes bankrupt, right, and
the court is... has to sort of decide how to deal with
all the creditors, it's not like it just gives all the money
to the earliest creditor, right? It's not like one person just empties
it out then full and then the next one whatever, there's some
type of a distribution that takes place.
And sometimes it can take many, many years.
Right. So anyway, so here even though the first one really is
entitled to the full amount first, maybe it doesn't always work out
that way. Okay, now we go on. נשא ראשונה. Nasas rishona. Now
we get to the more complicated case about the case about the
heirs and the... should we demonstrate, should we just draw space on
the board, about the heirs versus the creditors. Okay.
So here's ראובן Reuven
and he's married first to רחל, okay, and she brings in $20,000
into the estate, okay,
whatever, I mean that's the amount of her כתובה, kesuva her dowry,
her תוספת tosefes. or whatever, and then he marries לאה, okay, and
she brings in I don't know, let's say she brings in
10... When he dies, they're going to get that as an inheritance.
So that's stage number one. We'll use this color. Stage number one,
Rachel died.
Then stage number two, he died.
Okay. Okay, so now what happens? He died. They're coming and they
want to get כתובת בנין דכרין, Kesuvos Benin Dichrin. בנין דכרין. Benin
Dichrin. They want to get as a...... they want to get as
a ירושה, yerusha, they want to first take out their chunk, their
twenty thousand. Right? That's their chunk before everything gets divided equally. Okay.
Rachel's kids want to take their chunk out, okay, their twenty thousand
out. Leah's or her kids, right, maybe she has kids, maybe she
doesn't, they basically say... so they want their ירושה, yerusha, they come
and they say they want their כתובה kesuva. and they want their
ten thousand dollar כתובה, Kesubah okay? So that's what they're doing. These
kids here want their twenty thousand dollar ירושה yerusha and these kids
want to say, before you do that and before we worry about
that, we're coming in and we want our כתובה, Kesubah? okay? And
it says these guys are basically the debtor... the creditors. He's dead,
they have a lien on the estate and they come before any
division of any assets between the... and then, after they take that
out, then we'll look at the remaining estate and then we'll divvy
it up between the various heirs.
The whole estate is twenty.
Well, we don't know what the estate is.
Maybe it is.
Yeah. Well, that's what they're asking for. The whole estate might be...
the whole estate might be ten and they're just saying we're going
to take this and we're going to walk away, you're left with
nothing. But they have a ten thousand dollar claim, they want that
amount in terms of... in terms of the inheritance. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara
שמע מינה תלת, Shema mina telat, from this we infer three things.
שמע מינה אחת בחייו ואחת במותו, Shema mina achas bechayav ve'achas bemoso,
which is this case. One basically has died in the life and
one in the death. Okay, so in one case, you know, the...
by the heirs, their mother died while their father was alive. And
in the other case, you know, the mother either died after the
father died or they have rights that came as a result of
the death. That's just a way of describing this case, אחת בחייו
ואחת במותו. achas bechayav ve'achas bemoso.
ויש להן כתובת בנין דכרין. ve'yesh lahen Kesuvos Benin Dichrin. Okay, first
of all, that in principle, if there is enough money in the
estate, these guys are entitled to כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesuvos Benin Dichrin
ולא חיישינן לאינצוי, velo chaishinan le'intzuyei, and we're not afraid of fights.
ממאי, Mimai, how do you know? מדתני שניה ויורשיה קודמין ליורשי
ראשונה, mide'tanei sheniya ve'yorsheha kodmin le'yorshei rishona, Leah's heirs first get their
collection before the first ones get their inheritance. מקדם הוא דקדמי, mikdam
hu de'kadmei, they come first. האיכא שקלי, ha'ika shaklei, but if there's
enough money, they get it. Now, why shouldn't they get it? That's
the principle of כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesuvos Benin Dichrin. Because here's the
possible counter-argument. The possible counter-argument is that classic כתובת בנין דכרין, Kesuvos
Benin Dichrin right, would have been... classic כתובת בנין דכרין Kesubas Bnin
Dichrin. would have been that Leah died... Rachel died and Leah died,
and then Reuven died. Okay? And then basically we have this huge
estate, we've got to divide it up. And we say, okay, before
we divide it up, first everybody get out their כתובת בנין דכרין.
Kesubas Bnin Dichrin? You guys take out your twenty, you guys take
out your ten. Now we use the rest of the money and
we'll divide it up. In that case, Leah's kids can say, right,
okay, well, we also get, you know, yes you get your כתובת
בנין דכרין Kesubas Bnin Dichrin but we also get ours. So maybe
yours is bigger than ours or whatever, but at least we don't
have any legitimate complaint. Everybody is getting their inheritance from their mother,
their כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesubas Bnin Dichrin, That's when first... that's when
these two die and then Reuven dies. Okay, that's the classic case.
In this case, maybe we should be afraid that Leah's kids are
going to say, whoa, one minute! Why do you guys get a
special piece of the inheritance? We don't get a special piece of
the inheritance. You, in the inheritance division, you take a chunk out,
right, as part of your inheritance. We don't get to take a
chunk out as part of our inheritance before it gets divided. Yes,
our mother collected that, that was a debt. Right? Our mother collected
her ten thousand dollars, that was a debt. But now that our
father has died, why do you get a chunk of the inheritance
and we don't get a parallel chunk of the inheritance?
What do you mean? Each one is getting according to what was
in the document.
I understand. The bottom line is, okay, you didn't get it as
an inheritance. You got it because your mother collected her כתובה Kesubah.
as a debt. But nevertheless, yeah, you go try convincing that to
people when money is at stake. Okay? So they could still say,
it doesn't matter. Now we're talking as heirs and as יורשים. yorshim.
And as יורשים, yorshim, this was all our father's estate. Your mother
died first, she never collected her כתובה. Kesubah Why should you walk
off with a bigger part of the estate? Right, not fair. So
maybe we... maybe there's no rule of כתובת בנין דכרין Kesubas Bnin
Dichrin, when one set is there
as a... So maybe that would be an issue. You see now?
You see we're not concerned about that?
What does it mean? It could still be an issue unless it's
what we do.
Right, meaning we don't care about that. Okay, you're still entitled though
to their כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesubas Bnin Dichrin. That's principle number one.
Yes.
The additions to the כתובה Kesubah. are part of the כתובה? Kesubah.
Yes. That part... they're not inheritance,
they're the debt. That part goes to the creditors, the additions as
well as the 200 or 100 זוז? zuz?
What do you mean for the כתובת בנין
דכרין?
Kesubas
Bnin
Dichrin I'm not sure if I understand the definition of it, that's
why I'm asking. In other words, there's the 200 or 100 זוז.
zuz. Right.
That's why I gave 20,000.
Right, the כתובת בנין דכרין Kesubas Bnin Dichrin, is everything. This has
the 200 זוז zuz plus the, I don't know, $15,000
dowry, okay, plus the $4,800 תוספת. Right. Okay, all of that is
in the within the כתובה. Kesubah Okay, all of that, so she
didn't bring all of that in. Okay, the amount on the כתובה
Kesubah, was 20,000. It included 15,000 she brought in plus the 200
debt plus the 4,800 תוספת. And that was the face value of
the כתובה. Kesubah That's what she would have taken out if he
would have died first. Since he didn't die first and she died
first, that's the amount that's earmarked for her kids to get as
an inheritance before the other kids get as an inheritance.
But what I'm trying to understand is what's the distinction between inheritance
and and the what would go to a creditor first?
You follow what I'm asking? We said a creditor has precedence over...
Right, so here it's the same story, okay, except that because Reuven
died first, Reuven never inherited this from Leah. Leah comes to Reuven
as a creditor.
Same story, it's the same כתובה. Kesubah. Except when Rachel died first,
it's like he kept that money and then that money is going
to pass down to Rachel's
kids as an inheritance because he kept it.
Yes, he inherited it from Rachel.
Where and then but
then that's going to pass down to Rachel's kids. Okay, as part
of her inheritance.
And what's the definition of the word בני? Bnei?
Male sons. So it just means that your male sons, who are
anyway going to be my heirs, okay, but they're going to get
as a... they're going to take out of the estate before anything
else gets divided as part of their inheritance the amount of the
of the כתובה kesubah value.
All right.
As upset as Leah's kids might be or as Leah might be,
yeah, independent of what's written in any document, it's like what do
you want? Rachel died. Right, in other words, she died, so her
kid, her son inherited that chunk.
I understand that
they could still be upset, but it's not about adjudicating fairness of
a document.
Look, I think that if you didn't have this concept of כתובת
בנין דכרין, kesubas benin dichrin. you know, I think the intuitively you
would actually and even if you weren't just invested in it because
it was you were you know it meant money, I think the
intuitive perspective would have been like Leah's kids. You would have said
your mother didn't die, so she never collected her כתובה, kesubah so
this is all the money our father has. It's all it's all
the natural part of the estate. Why should you go ahead and
take a piece of it? Right?
Okay, so all right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
that's number one, that even in that case where they're coming from
different perspectives, Rachel's kids still get their their chunk. Okay, ושמע מינה,
u'shma mina, you also hear, כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה, Kesubah naasis moseer
lachaveirtah, that a כתובה Kesuva is considered leftover for the other כתובה.
Kesuva,
ממאיי, Mimai, how do you know? I'll just read and then I'll
say what it means. מדלא קתני אם יש שם מותר דינר, Midlo
katanie im yeish sham moseer dinar, because it didn't speak about if
there's an extra דינר dinar left over. What does that mean? It
means in a classic case of כתובת בנין דכרין, kesubas benin dichrin,
okay, the guy leaves over, his wives died first and then he
died, and he leaves over this estate, okay, and comes along Rachel's
kids and they get this piece of the estate because of that's
the amount their mother brought in, and comes along Leah's kids, okay,
let's say in the same example we had, okay, let's say again
let's say the case was basically that the wives died first and
then he died. Simple case, everybody gets everyone is coming as their
כתובת בנין דכרין. kesubas benin dichrin Okay, let's say they do that
and by the time they take out their mother's pieces there's absolutely
zero amount left in the estate. So you know what the הלכה
halacha is? Since nothing is left for a classic division for a
classic
biblical inherence, ירושה דאורייתא, yerusha de'oraisa, we we completely sort of you
know eliminate כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvat benin dichrin. and we say split
it all equally. Okay, so in this case right Rachel's kids would
have gotten a much huger chunk. But because if we were to
apply these rabbinic ideas of כתובת בנין דכרין, Kesuvat benin dichrin. we're
not left with any classic biblical division of a property based on
the normal rules of you know of inheritance, then then nobody gets
anything.
Then Rachel's kids would have taken their chunk, Leah would have gotten
nothing.
No, they would have gotten their full 10,000, but then there would
have been no money left over to apply
the... The classic rules of inheritance is you give the בכור bechor
twice as much, all the other kids get an equal amount. This
isn't applying classic rules of inheritance, this is you take this big
piece, you take that big piece. So you only will do this
Rabbinic idea of taking these chunks out if there's going to be
something left over in the end. Okay. And that's called מותר דינר,
mosar dinar, left over a דינר. dinar. A דינר dinar is more
than a פרוטה perutah but whatever. Twenty bucks. Literally, yeah. That's all
you need. You need there to be some symbolic amount left over
so we can apply, to split equally according to the normal rules.
And if not, then we completely eliminate that. Now, so that's the
normal rule. You need a מותר דינר mosar dinar in order to
apply כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesuvat benin dichrin. So here's the קשיא. kasha.
The question here is that it's an interesting concept.
That means for any Rabbinic institution you can't abrogate the דאורייתא. de-Oraisa.
I don't know if any, I don't know if I abstract things
as universally as that. Right. In this case, right. Now, here's the
question. Okay, in this case, let's say that all that's in the
estate is twenty thousand dollars, okay? And Rachel's kids here want to
go ahead and, or
what, and they just want to take it. Okay, comes along Leah's
kids and they're not here as כתובת בנין דכרין, Kesuvat benin dichrin
they're here as
creditors,
right?
They're here as creditors and they want their ten thousand dollars out
of the estate. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah says that they can
go ahead and do that, right? They take their ten thousand and
basically anything left
is taken by Rachel's kids. Well, why don't we say, no, no,
no, no, after they've taken their ten thousand,
Rachel's kids don't get כתובת בנין דכרין Kesuvat benin dichrin. because there's
no money left for equal division, right? So they lose their special
right, right?
Yeah, right? Because there's no money left over. But the משנה Mishnah
doesn't say that. And the גמרא says here's why the משנה Mishna
doesn't say that. Because when Leah's kids come as creditors and take
the ten thousand, the estate is paying off the creditors. Imagine this
hadn't been Leah. Imagine this had just been, you know, Fred. And
Fred was coming and he said I got a ten thousand dollar
lien on the estate, okay? So the whole estate is paying him.
That's like the מותר דינר mosar dinar because even if all the
heirs had inherited it equally and it was a normal Biblical division,
they'd all have to use that money to pay off a creditor,
right? So this is like, you know, extra money of the estate.
So it could be that the estate needed twenty thousand
and one dollar. You know what I mean? It could be that
it needed that extra like one dollar there as it were, you
know, so that if there were no creditors they would have taken
that and then there would have been that extra דינר dinar to
divide. But the fact that now that the creditors come and you
don't have that extra dollar, that doesn't matter because that extra dollar
was used to pay the creditors, okay? So therefore, even though after
Leah comes, there's, you know, Rachel walks
away with all the rest, it still seemed like there was money
there for the Biblical division of assets because the fact that there
was a little bit extra there, that one extra dollar, it was
taken away by a creditor, so that meant that extra money was
used to pay the creditor, okay? So even though it wasn't left
after the creditor walked away, it was there beforehand and used to
pay the creditor.
It really was only thirty thousand this estate. We don't even need
it to be thirty thousand and one.
Right. We don't even need it to be thirty thousand, it could
be twenty thousand and one. And they carve and they take ten
thousand whatever and they're left with
ten thousand and one.
Right. It could have been anything as long as there was a
creditor who was being paid a debt. The Biblical requirement assumes a
ירושה, yerusha, a pure ירושה yerusha situation. Right. If there's debt, then
you fulfill the other. Right.
Now if there was just twenty thousand, then I'm not sure we
would say that because then it's like because then it like eliminates
the creditor, there's nothing extra left. Okay. But if without having looked
at the creditor there was extra and now there's just no extra
because the creditor was paid off, the reason there's no extra is
because the creditor was paid off, but it was paid off by
the estate, which means the normal inheritance of the estate.
Okay, so the משנה says
this, ושמע מינה כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה, U-shema mina kesubah na’asis mosar
le-chaverta,
that the כתובה Kesuva, itself is sort of like it's considered to
be the extra amount, the amount that was collected here for the
כתובה Kesuva, to allow the Rachel's kids the friend חברותא, chavrusa, the
other חברותא, chavrusa, Rachel's kids to get their piece. דמאי לאו דתני
דאיכא מותר דינר D’mai lav de-tani de-ika mosar dinar because it doesn't
limit it to a case that there was an extra dollar around
even if there wasn't an extra dollar around.
Okay. ושמע מינה, U-shema mina, you also see, כתובת בנין דכרין לא
טרפי ממשעבדי, Kesubas benin dichrin lo tarfei mi-mesha’abdei,
that the
Rachel's kids who are getting because of this idea of male heirs,
they don't collect from things that have a lien on them. How
do you know it? דאי סלקא דעתך טרפי ממשעבדי, De-i salka dach-tach
tarfei mi-mesha’abdei, if they collect from property. with lien, מייתו בני ראשונה
וטרפי מבני שנייה. meito bnei rishona v'tarfei mibnei shnia.
Why don't the first kids come and collect from the second kids,
which means what?
Right, meaning this is Michael's point, which is we've been assuming, I've
been describing this whole thing that these kids are getting it here
as heirs. Okay, but another way of understanding why Rachel's kids are
entitled to is not as heirs but as creditors. Okay, right? So
that's a different way of conceptualizing it. That her kids get when
Ruben dies and they get as creditors. Okay, so it says no,
obviously they're not getting as creditors, because if they were creditors, and
they were creditors, who would have first rights?
Whoever got married first.
Rachel's kids would have first rights because they're just now finally collecting
their mother's כתובה as creditors. So it says the fact that Leah
gets first rights shows that the kids here are getting it not
as creditors, but as heirs. So when it's creditors against heirs, the
creditors always come to collect from the heirs. But if these kids
were getting it as a late collection of their mother's כתובה, then
they would come before Leah's kids. All right? Okay, so ושמע מינה
כתובת בנין דכרין לא טרפי ממשעבדי Ushma mina Kesuvat benin dichrin lo
tarfei mimeshabedi which is basically a way of saying that they're not
getting it as creditors. דאי סלקא דעתך טרפי ממשעבדי מייתו בני ראשונה
וטרפי מבני שנייה, dei salka daitach tarfei mimeshabedi meito bnei rishona v'tarfei
mibnei shnia, the
first kids should get it before the second kids. Okay. מתקיף לה
רב אשי. Matkif lah Rav Ashi. Rav Ashi asked this: ממאי? mimai?
How do you know any of that is true? דילמא לעולם אימא
לך אחת בחייו ואחת במותו אין כאן כתובת בנין דכרין. Dilma l'olam
eima lach achas b'chaiv v'achas b'moso ein kan Kesuvat benin dichrin. Maybe
I would say that if it's this scenario that some are, one
died when he was alive and the other one basically after he
died, so some are coming as בנין דכרין benin dichrin and the
other are coming as creditors, maybe they don't get כתובת בנין דכרין.
Kesuvat benin dichrin, ומאי קודמין? Umai kodmin? And what does it mean
that Leah's kids come first? It means לנחלה קתני. l'nachala katani.
It means, hold on, let me just check it,
right, get,
no, so
what does it mean that these come first? It means that they
come first in terms of the inheritance, which means the following. We
are reading this that it says Leah's kids come first and they
get their mother's כתובה, and then Rachel's kids are entitled to their
כתובת בנין דכרין. Kesuvat benin dichrin, Okay? Maybe it doesn't mean that.
Maybe it means Leah's kids come first and they get their mother's
כתובה, and then everything else gets divided equally. Meaning, maybe when it
says Leah's kids come first, the subtext, the implication is not and
then Rachel's kids get their special inheritance. Maybe it means Rachel's kids
come first, they get it as creditors, and then normal נחלה nachala
applies and maybe Rachel's kids get zip in terms of their special
rights. Okay? So he says ומאי קודמין? umai kodmin? What does it
mean that Leah's kids come first? לנחלה קתני. l'nachala katani. It means
that they come first before the normal inheritance takes place, but maybe
Rachel's kids don't get any special inheritance. וכי תימא יורשי ראשונה למה
לי? V'chi teima yorshei rishona lama li? So why is it calling
Rachel's kids the heirs if they no longer have a status of
heirs? איידי דתני שנייה ויורשיה תני נמי יורשי ראשונה Aidi d'tani shnia
v'yorsheha tani nami yorshei rishona because it says Leah or her heirs,
so it says the heirs of Rachel, but they're really not coming
as heirs. So maybe the משנה does not mean that Rachel's kids
actually get their כתובת בנין דכרין. Maybe they get absolutely nothing special.
ודקאמרת כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה? U'd'ka'amart Kesuva na'asis mosar l'chaverta? Your other
point, which is that assuming that it is working based on the
principle of כתובת בנין דכרין and you wanted to say that there
doesn't have to be a dollar left over because that was already
used to pay off Leah's heirs and that was the dollar left
over. דילמא לעולם אימא לך אין כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה. Dilma l'olam
eima lach ein Kesuva na'asis mosar l'chaverta. Maybe that's not true. Maybe
after the creditors are paid, you need there to be a dollar
left over in order to do the כתובת בנין דכרין. והכא הוא
דאיכא מותר דמינא. V'hacha hu d'ika mosar demina. And here we're talking
that that's the case, that when it says Leah's kids come and
take and then Rachel, assuming we are saying that Rachel's kids get
this כתובת בנין דכרין, we would be talking assuming that there was
still money left over afterwards. But if there wasn't money left over
afterwards, maybe we wouldn't say it.
You mean there was thirty thousand and one?
There would be thirty thousand and one. Yes. So okay, you said
since it didn't say explicitly that there had to be money left
over, it means it didn't have to be money left over. No.
Maybe it was assuming that there was money left over. So you
made two inferences and I can say that either one is wrong.
You assumed after Leah took, Rachel's kids got as heirs of כתובת
בנין דכרין, it never said that explicitly. Maybe
it. Maybe it's assuming that there would be money left over after
they took, but maybe if there wasn't, רחל's kids wouldn't get it.
So basically you wanted to make these assumptions that basically strengthen רחל's
kids and her and their right; maybe neither of them are correct.
Now the פשט pshat still is in the first approach, but he's
just saying that it's not necessarily מוכרח, muchrach, it's not necessarily true,
it's not explicitly that way. All right, so we'll see more about
this. Unfortunately, we're already over for our time today, so we'll see
more of this tomorrow.
See you tomorrow. Take care.